A Guide to the Governor William H. Cabell Executive Papers, 1805-1808
Library of Virginia
Governors from other states comprise a significant amount of correspondence received by the Governor. This correspondence mostly relates to amendments to the U.S. Constitution and the exchange of laws. Included are letters from the following governors: William C.C. Claiborne, Territory of Orleans; John Milledge, Georgia; Paul Hamilton, South Carolina; Christopher Greenup, Kentucky; Joseph Bloomfield, New Jersey; Nathaniel Mitchell & George Truitt, Delaware; Robert Wright, Maryland; Israel Smith, Vermont; John Trumball, Connecticut; and John Langdon, New Hampshire. William C.C. Claiborne transmits a copy of the laws for the Territory of Orleans (1806 Feb. 7). John Milledge, Georgia, writes to George Jefferson regarding the sale of the negro Bob (1806 March 31). Paul Hamilton, South Carolina, requests information on the expenses, rules of confinement, etc., for the Penitentiary in preparation for the establishment of a similar facility in South Carolina (1806 June 18). Christopher Greenup, Kentucky, encloses a copy of the several resolutions of the Kentucky General Assembly regarding their attachment to the federal government & their confidence in the same (1806 Dec. 22). Governor Greenup also encloses an address by the Kentucky Assembly respecting the turnpike or toll-gate erected in the gap of the Cumberland Mountain (1806 Dec. 27). Joseph Bloomfield, New Jersey, transmits a resolution of the New Jersey General Assembly regarding the proposed amendment to the U.S. Constitution (1807 Jan. 27); responds to the resolution of Virginia proposing an amendment to the U.S. Constitution for the removal of senators (1808 March 3); transmits copies of the acts passed by the New Jersey Assembly (1808 April 23); and acknowledges receipt of Dr. Madison's map of Virginia (1808 April 25). Nathaniel Mitchell, Delaware, encloses a resolution of the Delaware General Assembly approving the amendment to the U.S. Constitution proposed by Kentucky to restrain the judiciary power of the U.S. courts (1807 Feb. 25). Later, Gov. George Truitt transmits a resolution of the Delaware General Assembly disapproving of the amendment proposed by the Vermont General Assembly respecting the dismissal of Federal Judges (1808 Feb. 15) and acknowledges receipt of the map of Virginia & acts of the Virginia Assembly (1808 May 16). On 22 Jan. 1807, Robert Wright transmits a resolution instructing the senators & representatives of Maryland in Congress to prohibit the importation of slaves into the United States from Africa, the West Indies, etc. Israel Smith, Vermont, transmits a resolution of the Vermont General Assembly to procure an amendment to the U.S. Constitution empowering the President to remove any of the U.S. judges by a majority vote of the House & two-thirds of the Senate (1807 Dec. 7). John Trumball, Connecticut transmits resolutions of amendments to the U.S. Constitution in opposition to Virginia's proposed amendment (1808 June 10). Lastly, John Langdon, New Hampshire, transmits a resolution expressing gratification for Virginia in sending a map of the state (1808 June 25).
Additional significant correspondence includes the following: the President & Directors of the Dismal Swamp Company reporting on the progress made by the company (1805 Dec. 21); Edmund Randolph re. the case of gunstocks kept by Capt. Potter intended for Capt. Clarke & the Manufactory of Arms (1805 Dec. 30); Thomas Underwood, Superintendent of the Public Warehouse, re. making the roof of the warehouse able to receive flour for storage by providing a hoisting apparatus (1806 Jan. 10); William Fulcher proposing to purchase the condemned negroes in the Penitentiary for transportation beyond the limits of the U.S. (1806 Jan. 31); William McKim to John Clarke re. an estimate for a dome, etc., as a steeple to the Virginia Manufactory of Arms (1806 Feb. 26); William Foushee resigning as a member of the Privy Council (1806 April 11); Edward Carrington, Mayor of Richmond, re. the case of Billy, a negro slave sentenced to death (1806 April 28); Paul Carrington resigning as a judge of the Court of Appeals (1807 Jan. 7); William McKim re. the painting of the cupola of the Manufactory of Arms (1807 Jan. 15); Hugh Phelps re. the treasonable enterprise of Aaron Burr & his associates (1807 Feb. 14); Arthur Campbell encl. a letter from Meriwether Lewis, Capt. of the 1st U.S. Infantry Regt., re. Walker's line between Virginia & North Carolina (1807 Feb. 23); Alexander Spotswood to Edmund Randolph re. manuscript books containing his grandfather's correspondence with the British Ministry (1807 April 20); Henry Lee re. the present militia system (1807 Nov. 23); Thomas Mathews re. the British ships Itruria and Triumph (1808 Jan. 11); Robert Gamble resigning from the Board of Visitors of the Penitentiary (1808 Jan. 23); John Tyler re. the Chancery Courts & the alteration of the district law (1808 Feb. 10); William W. Hening re. the President's recommendation of thirty thousand additional troops and the continuance of the embargo against Great Britain (1808 Feb. 25); William W. Hening re. Virginia's accounts with the War Dept. (1808 Feb. 28 & 1808 March 1); Creed Taylor resigning as a visitor of the Penitentiary (1808 April 29); Henry Foxall, Columbia Furnace, offering to make all the machinery necessary for casting, boring, & turning cannon for the factory in Richmond (1808 April 28); William W. Hening re. Virginia's claims against the United States (1808 April 17, 23, 19, & 27); Samuel G. Adams requesting the use of all the surplus water from the two springs after supplying the Capitol & barracks (1808 June 25); Samuel A. Otis forwarding three copies of the journals of the U.S. Senate (1808 July 2); Henry Blow, William Blow, & Samuel Blunt, Trustees of the Nottoway Tribe of Indians, re. the tribe and including a list of male members, their age, & employments (1808 July 18); Patrick Magruder transmitting copies of the journal of the House of Representatives (1808 Sept. 15); Henry Blow, William Blow, & Samuel Blunt, Trustees of the Nottoway Tribe of Indians, re. the sale of their lands in 1792 or 1793 (1808 Oct. 8); Thomas Mathews enclosing a letter from William Sharp, Lt. Col. of the 54th Regt., re. a suspected insurrection of slaves in Norfolk including depositions (1808 Nov. 18); and Richard Young, surveyor on the public property, enclosing a resolution of the Richmond Common Council re. the names of streets, lanes, & alleys not previously named by the Directors of Public Buildings (1808 Dec. 7).
Other noteworthy items include: bonds of William Moseley as Treasurer (1806 Jan. 1; 1807 Jan. 7; & 1808 Jan. 12); a report of the Committee appointed to enquire into the causes & circumstances attending the breaking of the Penitentiary by the convicts and their escape (1806 Feb. 8); an estimate for building a foundry at the Manufactory of Arms by William McKim & Robert Hyde (1806 Feb. 22); an estimate for building a boring mill at the Manufactory of Arms by William McKim & Robert Hyde (1806 Feb. 22); a list of slaves reprieved for transportation & sold by the Commonwealth (1806 March 8); a bond of William & Robert McKim to build a cupola with a dome roof & belfry for the Virginia Manufactory of Arms (1806 March 10); a report of the Committee appointed to visit the Penitentiary & examine minutely into the manner in which the rules & regulations are carried into effect (1806 April 5); an estimate & drawing of a crane by William Street for the Public Warehouse (1806 May 26); a note & plan by R.B. James for a canal to the Public Warehouse (1806 Sept. 27); proclamations by Governor Cabell & Lt. Gov. Alexander McRae offering a reward for the capture of various criminals (1806 Oct. 14; 1807 April 2; 1808 Jan. 15; 1808 April 30; 1808 July 27; 1808 June 25; 1808 Aug. 5; 1808 Aug. 19; & 1808 Sept. 23); proceedings of the Monthly Visitors of the Penitentiary (1807 April 24; 1807 Oct. 30; 1807 Dec. 30; 1808 Feb. 2; & 1808 July 25); the bond of Abraham Douglas as Keeper of the Penitentiary (1807 May 16); a proclamation of Governor Cabell to hold court for Culpeper County in the Mason's Hall until the courthouse is refurbished (1807 June 20); a general statement showing the cost of articles brought by the agent for manufacture in the Penitentiary (1807 Sept. 1); a report of the Visitors of the Penitentiary regarding the price of nails manufactured there (1807 Oct. 26); bonds of Samuel Pleasants, Jr., as Public Printer (1807 Dec. 9 & 1808 Dec. 10); a list of cavalry officers (1807 Dec. 22); a report of the Committee to examine the quality of the arms in the Manufactory of Arms (1808 Jan. 22); a resolution from Samuel A. Otis, Secretary of the U.S. Senate, for a Committee to inquire into the expediency of amending the act to establish the judicial courts of the U.S. (1808 Feb. 21); a proclamation by Gov. Cabell authorizing the Warwick County Court to be held at the house of Wade Mountfort at Rich Neck until the former can be repaired or rebuilt (1808 Feb. 24); an inventory of articles on hand at the Penitentiary (1808 June 1); a report of the Committee appointed to reprove arms at the Manufactory (1808 July 22); an estimate by Samuel Brooke of the greater & lesser seals for the Chancery Courts including drawings of the state seal (1808 Sept. 2); a pay roll of officers of Virginia Militia & an abstract of expenditures in the Quarter Master's Dept. in the service of the United States (1808 Sept. 11); an account current of the U.S. with Robert C. Jennings acting as Pay Master of the Virginia Militia (1808 Sept. 30); and a report of the Committee on the state of the Register's Office following the death of William Price which provides a list of all the materials in the office such as grant books, plats & certificates, etc. (1808 Oct. 15).
SERIES II: Chesapeake-Leopard Affair Files. This series primarily contains incoming correspondence related to the Chesapeake-Leopard Affair from June and November 1807. In addition to correspondence, there are petitions, proceedings, advice of Council, resolutions, reports, and other sundry items. These files were originally separated to provide a ready-reference to researchers. The documents originate from several chief sources including: Thomas Mathews, Thomas Newton, William Dudley, the Council of State, & miscellaneous sources.
Thomas Mathews, Brigadier General of the Virginia Militia, provides the most correspondence related to the Chesapeake-Leopard Affair. Mathews furnishes regular reports to the Governor respecting the location and movement of the British Squadron in July & August 1807. In addition, Mathews often provides copies of correspondence sent & received by him. Mathews writes the Governor on 23 June 1807 enclosing a copy of his letter to James Madison, Secretary of State, informing him of the confrontation between the Chesapeake and the British warship Leopard off the Capes of Virginia on 22 June. On 26 June, Mathews informs the Governor of the appearance of a British lieutenant in Norfolk delivering dispatches to the British Consul. In his letter of 8 July, Mathews discusses the conditions of Forts Norfolk & Nelson and preparations in the event of a British attack. Mathews encloses his letter to Commodore Douglas transmitting the President's proclamation and a letter from G. Newton who provides an account of his meeting with Douglas in delivering the proclamation (1807 July 13). Mathews estimates the force of the squadron including the number of marines & seamen in his letter dated 15 July. His letter of 17 July forwards his instructions to Capt. Shepard & Capt. Robert B. Taylor to prevent ships from making excursions on shore for supplies. In the same letter, he also encloses a dispatch from Richard E. Lee regarding his meeting with Commodore Douglas. On 28 July, Mathews encloses several letters to and from Maj. Littleton Tazewell regarding instructions in exchanging flags with the British Squadron and Tazewell's meeting with Capt. Humphries on board the Leopard. Similarly, Mathews encloses a copy of his letter to Capt. Thomas Hardy, orders to Maj. Tazewell, and Tazewell's report of the capture of two British officers & three seamen attempting to procure supplies (1807 Aug. 3). In addition, Mathews encloses the report of Capt. Robert Taylor regarding fugitive slaves and Americans on board the British ships (1807 Aug. 7). Particularly interesting is Mathews' letter of 15 Aug. enclosing Capt. Robert Taylor's report containing a list of persons examined on board the Triumph & Columbine as possible America citizens. On 13 Aug., Mathews informs the Governor of the arrival of a new ship flying the flag of a British Vice Admiral, supposedly Admiral George Cranfield Berkley. Lastly, Mathews encloses his letter & general orders to Maj. Thomas Newton regarding instructions to prevent the British Squadron from taking supplies and water from Virginia's shores (1807 Aug. 26).
Other sundry letters from Mathews relate to the following topics: resolutions of the inhabitants of Norfolk & Portsmouth (1807 June 25); resolutions of citizens prohibiting intercourse & supplies with British ships (1807 June 29); the location of the British Squadron and reported threats by the British for a supply of water & provisions (1807 July 3); the escape of slaves who were received by the British ships (1807 July 20); citizens furnishing labor for the erection of batteries at Fort Norfolk and the necessity of erecting works at Craney Island, Washington Point, & intermediate points along the river (1807 July 29); provisions for the British Ship Columbine (1807 Aug. 9, 17, & 22); Americans on board Capt. Hardy's ships (1807 Aug. 10); Commodore Stephen Decatur's gunboats (1807 Aug. 18); and his visit to the posts established at the Pleasure House & Lynhaven Inlet (1807 Aug. 21).
Thomas Newton, Major Commandant at Norfolk, provides daily status reports of the British Squadron within the Capes in September & October 1807. On 31 Aug., Newton writes regarding the detachment of militia under his command and the liberation of the American seamen & a slave on board the British Squadron. Newton also transmits copies of letters from Sir Robert Laurie, Capt. H.M.S. Milan, regarding impressed American seamen and a report by Capt. John Reade & Capt. Tully Robinson (1807 Sept. 4). On 16 Sept., Newton writes concerning the landing of men from one of the British ships and the desertion of five British sailors. His letters of 26 & 29 August relate to the court martial of John Bourke, a private in Capt. Peter Nestle's Company of Artillery, accused of striking an officer. The proceedings on Bourke's court martial are enclosed in Newton's second letter. Newton encloses another letter from Capt. Robert Laurie on 1 Oct. regarding American seamen on board British ships. Lastly, in his latter dated 11 Oct., Newton requests the discharge of men under the command of Capt. Nestle. In this letter, Newton also mentions his leaving command on 15 Oct. Newton also comments on the defenseless situation of this part of the country and recommends the construction of a fort on Craney Island. After Oct. 15, Capt. John Reade, 20th Regt., provided the Governor with status reports on the British Squadron (1807 Oct. 21, 24, & 25). In addition, along with these reports, Reade encloses a report of the state of arms in his detachment (Oct. 21) and writes concerning the arrest of two men in his command (25 Oct.).
William Dudley, Major Commandant at Hampton, too provides significant correspondence respecting the Chesapeake-Leopard Affair. In his letter dated 14 July, Dudley encloses a return of the troops on duty at Hampton & its vicinity. On 18 July, Dudley details the British ship Triumph's boarding of a pilot boat in an attempt to request them to receive & deliver a letter to the British Consul. Major Dudley encloses a letter from Capt. T.M. Hardy, H.M.S. Triumph, regarding dispatches from the Commander in Chief to the Envoy Extraordinary at Washington, along with letters for the Consul at Norfolk, and his orders for Capt. Bradshaw to proceed to Hampton Roads to deliver the dispatches & complete his provisions (1807 Aug. 2).
The Council of State provides regular advice to the Governor respecting the Chesapeake-Leopard Affair. On 25 June, the Council advise the Governor to dispatch an express to the President informing him of the capture of the Chesapeake. The Council also advise the Governor to write the President for the purpose of preventing the troops on board the British Squadron now blockading Norfolk from landing (1807 July 6). Other sundry advice by the Council documents a detachment of militia to march to Norfolk with two companies of infantry from Col. George W. Smith of Richmond & a company of infantry by Maj. James Byrne of Petersburg (1807 July 6) and captured marines & midshipmen belonging to the British Squadron (1807 July 27).
Miscellaneous documents relating to the Chesapeake-Leopard Affair include the following: a request for the advice of the Governor & Council regarding the capture of the Chesapeake (1807 June 23); proceedings of the Ledger Office in Norfolk (1807 June 24); proceedings of citizens of Williamsburg (1807 June 26); proceedings of citizens of Portsmouth (1807 June 27); proceedings of citizens of Hampton (1807 June 28); a letter from James Madison enclosing a proclamation by President Jefferson requiring all armed vessels under the British flag to depart U.S. waters (1807 July 2); a letter from Richard E. Lee, Mayor of Norfolk, enclosing a copy of correspondence between him and J.E. Douglas regarding the resolution of 29 June prohibiting correspondence between the British Consul at Norfolk and the British ships in Lynhaven Bay (1807 July 4); a letter from Littleton W. Tazewell enclosing a copy of his letter to Richard E. Lee regarding his conversation with Commodore Douglas and his general mistrust of their intentions (1807 July 6); a letter from Henry Dearborn, War Dept., regarding measures to organize, arm, & equip one hundred thousand militia (1807 July 6); a letter from R.G. Robb enclosing resolutions of a meeting of citizens of Port Royal (1807 July 9); a letter from Thomson Mason enclosing proceedings of a meeting of citizens of Fairfax County (1807 July 15); a letter from Robert Gamble enclosing a roll of the Silver Greys associated for the purpose of guarding Richmond (1807 July 22); a letter from E.T. Dupont de Nemours & Company, manufacturers of gun powder in Wilmington, Delaware, offering to supply Virginia with cannon & musket powder (1807 July 27); a letter from Governor Christopher Greenup enclosing proceedings of a meeting of citizens of Franklin (1807 July 28); resolutions from a meeting of citizens of Washington County (1807 Aug. 2); a letter from John Clarke regarding the mounting of heavy cannon on carriages to repel the marine force including a drawing of gun placements along a river full of enemy ships (1807 Aug. 2); a letter from Henry Dearborn, War Dept., requesting the Governor to hold all volunteer associations as part of the quota of militia in readiness (1807 Aug. 3); a letter from Henry Dearborn, War Dept., regarding the pay of the militia & camp equipage (1807 Aug. 3); a pay roll of Capt. Edmund C. Goodwin's Company of Light Infantry under Col. John Mayo (1807 Aug. 5); a letter from Thomas Jefferson returning papers received on the 18th (1807 Aug. 21); a letter from Henry Lee regarding the volunteer levy & preparations for war such as guarding seaports at Norfolk & the York River and arming free negroes (1807 Aug. 24); a letter from Samuel Coleman regarding the arming & equipping of the men in the requisition of the Secretary of War (1807 Aug. 27); and a letter from Capt. Peter Nestle transcribing a letter from Henry Dearborn regarding the discharge of the two companies of militia now in service (1807 Nov. 2).
Arrangement
William H. Cabell's Executive papers are organized into two series. Series have been designated for Chronological files and the Chesapeake-Leopard Affair. Each series is arranged chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Flournoy, H. W., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, January 1, 1799-Dec. 31, 1807, VOL. IX, Richmond: J.H. O'Bannon, Superintendent of Public Printing, 1890.
Flournoy, H. W., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, January 1, 1808-December 31, 1835, VOL. X, Richmond: James E. Goode, Printer, 1892.
Separated Material
Oversized materials have been separated into Oversized (Clamshell Box) and Oversized (Newspaper Box).
Contents List
- Series I: Chronological Files
  - 1805
    - December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1806
    - January
      - 1-14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - February
      - 2-15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 18-28 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - March
      - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - 21-31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - April
      - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - May
      - 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - June
      - 1-10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 11-30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - July
      - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - August
      - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - September
      - 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - October (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - November (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - December
      - 1-20 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - 22-30 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1807
    - January
      - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - February
      - 1-14 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 16-28 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - March
      - 2-12 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - April
      - 1-20 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - 22-30 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - May
      - 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - June
      - 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 16-30 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - July
      - 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - August
      - 3-15 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - 17-31 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - September
      - 1-10 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 11-20 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - 21-30 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - October
      - 1-20 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - 21-31 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - November
      - 1-14 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - December
      - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1808
    - January
      - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - February
      - 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - 16-29 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - March
      - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 16-23 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - 24-30 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - April
      - 1-10 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - 11-20 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - 21-30 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - May
      - 1-14 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - 15-30 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - June
      - 1-15 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - 16-23 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - 24-30 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - July
      - 1-8 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 9-20 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - 21-27 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - 28-31 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - August
      - 1-5 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - 6-15 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - 16-31 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - September
      - 1-10 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - 11-20 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - 22-30 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - October
      - 1-10 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - 11-20 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - 21-31 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Pardons - Gillespie, Thomas (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - November
      - 1-10 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - 11-20 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - 21-30 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - December (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Series II: Chesapeake-Leopard Affair
  - 1807
    - June (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - July